<?xml-model href="sherlock.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
    <metadata>
        <series>Series: Sherlock Holmes</series>
        <show>Show: A Scandal in Bohemia</show>
        <date when="1945-12-10">Date: Dec 10 1945</date>
        <castList>CAST <cast ref="#announcer">ANNOUNCER</cast>
            <cast ref="#watson">DR. JOHN H. WATSON</cast>
            <cast ref="#holmes">SHERLOCK HOLMES</cast>
            <cast ref="#kingBohemia">KING OF BOHEMIA, German accent</cast>
            <cast ref="#bartemder">BARTENDER</cast>
            <cast ref="#1stCabman">1ST CABMAN (2 lines)</cast>
            <cast ref="#norton">GEOFFREY NORTON (1 line)</cast>
            <cast ref="#adler">IRENE ADLER (PRONOUNCED eye-REE-nee ADD-ler)</cast>
            <cast ref="#coach">COACHMAN (1 line)</cast>
            <cast ref="#2ndCabman">2ND CABMAN (3 lines)</cast>
            <cast ref="#alfie">ALFIE</cast>
            <cast ref="#pat">PAT (1 line)</cast>
            <cast ref="#hattie">HATTIE</cast>
            <cast ref="#ernie">ERNIE (4 lines)</cast>
            <cast ref="#bert">BERT (2 lines)</cast>
            <cast ref="#maid">MAID (4 lines)</cast>
        </castList>
    </metadata>
    <scene>
        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker> This episode from the life of <mention ref="#holmes"
                >Sherlock Holmes </mention> will be transmitted to our men and women overseas by
            short wave and through the worldwide facilities of the Armed Forces Radio Service. Petri
            Wine brings you-- </ln>

        <music> STING </music>

        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker> Basil Rathbone and Nigel Bruce in "The New Adventures of
                <mention ref="#holmes">Sherlock Holmes </mention>." </ln>

        <music> UP AND OUT </music>

        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker> The Petri family -- the family that took time to bring you
            good wine -- invites you to listen to <mention ref="#watson">Dr. Watson </mention> tell
            us another exciting adventure he shared with his old friend, that master detective,
                <mention ref="#holmes">Sherlock Holmes </mention>. And you know something? I had an
            adventure tonight I wish you could have shared with me. I had a steak about, oh, an inch
            and a half thick, tender and juicy, and with it I had a glass of Petri California
            Burgundy. Now there's a combination -- steak and Petri Burgundy. That Petri Burgundy is
            a perfect mealtime wine. It's a rich, red wine that's hearty and full of flavor --
            flavor that comes right from the heart of the grape. And don't think that Petri Burgundy
            is only good with steak -- it'll make a hamburger sandwich taste like a feast, too. Try
            Petri Burgundy with any meat or meat dish. It's just wonderful! And serve it proudly,
            too, because after all, the name Petri is the proudest name in the history of American
            wines. </ln>

        <music> THEME </music>

        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker> And now I know <mention ref="#watson">Dr. Watson
            </mention>'s waiting for us, so let's go in and join him. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> KNOCK ON DOOR </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>
            <expression> BEHIND DOOR </expression> Come in. Come in, come in. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> DOOR OPENS </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker> Good evening, <mention ref="#watson">Dr. Watson </mention>. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Good evening, Mr. Bartell. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> DOOR SHUTS </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> You're quite muffled up tonight, I see. Overcoat, scarf and
            gloves. Slip 'em off and come and join me by the fire. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker> Thanks, doctor. Quite a nip in the air tonight. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Yes, there is indeed. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker> Well, doctor, you told us last week that tonight's story
            centered around the activities of a brilliant and beautiful woman. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Yes, my boy. Her name was Irene Adler. But I never knew Holmes
            to refer to her by any other name than "The Woman." </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker> She sounds mighty intriguing. How did you happen to meet up
            with her? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Well, I'll tell you the story from the beginning. One night --
            it was on the twentieth of March, Eighteen Hundred and Eighty-Eight, to be exact -- I
            was returning home from a visit to a patient, when my steps led me through Baker Street.
            Since my marriage, I hadn't seen much of <mention ref="#holmes">Sherlock Holmes
            </mention> and-- </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker> You couldn't resist stopping by Two-Twenty-One B, I'm sure,
            doctor. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Of course I couldn't. As I stood outside the well-remembered
            door, I looked up at the lighted windows and saw the tall, spare figure of my old friend
            pass twice in dark silhouette against the blind. He was pacing the room swiftly,
            eagerly, with his head sunk on his chest and his hands clasped behind him. To me, who
            knew his every mood and habit, his attitude and manner told their own story. He was hot
            on the scent of some new problem. I rang the bell and a few moments later, found myself
            standing before him. <expression> FADES OUT </expression>
        </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>
            <expression> FADES IN </expression> Marriage suits you, <mention ref="#watson">Watson
            </mention>. You look in splendid shape. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Yes, Holmes, I'm feeling very well, thanks. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> And in practice again, I see. You didn't tell me that you'd
            gone back into harness. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>
            <expression> SURPRISED </expression> Oh? How do you know? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Elementary, my dear chap. If a gentleman walks into my rooms
            smelling of iodoform, with a black mark of nitrate of silver on his right forefinger and
            a bulge on the left side of his hat to show where he has secreted his stethoscope, I
            should be dull, indeed, if I didn't pronounce him to be an active member of the medical
            profession. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>
            <expression> CHUCKLES </expression> Same as ever, Holmes. By the way, I'm, uh-- I'm not
            interrupting you, am I? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Yes, you are, old fellow, but it's a most welcome
            interruption. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> You're working on a new case? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> It looks like it. This letter arrived by the last post today.
            It's undated, and has neither signature nor address. Read it. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>
            <expression> MUMBLES) Let's have a look. (READS) "There will call upon you tonight, at a
                quarter to eight o'clock, a gentleman who desires to consult you upon a matter of
                the very deepest moment. Your recent services to one of the royal houses of Europe
                have shown that you are one who may safely be trusted. This account of you we have
                from all quarters received." (TO HIMSELF) Hm! (READS) "Be in your chamber, then, at
                that hour, and do not take it amiss if your visitor wears a mask." (TO HOLMES
            </expression> Great Scott, it all sounds very mysterious. What do you imagine it means? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Look carefully at the note, <mention ref="#watson">Watson
            </mention>. What do you deduce from it? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Oh, let's see. Well, the man who wrote it was presumably
            well-to-do. Such paper couldn't be bought for under half a crown a packet. And it's
            peculiarly strong and stiff. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Peculiar -- that's the very word. It's not an English paper at
            all. Hold it up to the light. You notice anything? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Yes. There's a large "E" with a small "g"-- </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>
            <expression> AGREES </expression> Mm hm. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> --and a large "G" with a small "t" woven into the texture of
            the paper. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> What does that suggest to you? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> The name of the maker, no doubt; or perhaps his monogram. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Not at all, my dear fellow. The "G" with the small "t" stands
            for "Gesellschaft," which is the German for "Company." </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> And the "E - g"? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> That stands for Egria. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Egria? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> It's in a German-speaking country in Bohemia, not far from
            Carlsbad. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> So the paper was made in Bohemia. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Undoubtedly. And the man who wrote the note is a German. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> How do you know that? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Observe the curious construction of the sentence, "This
            account of you we have from all quarters received." A Frenchman or a Russian could not
            have written that. It's the German who is so discourteous to his verbs. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> VICTORIAN DOORBELL JANGLES, OFF </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> There's your client now. I'd better go, Holmes. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> No, no, no, no -- unless you have to. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Well, I could stay; I thought perhaps that-- </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Then, my dear chap, stay. by all means. I'm lost without my
            Boswell, and this promises to be interesting. I told Mrs. Hudson to let the masked
            visitor come upstairs unannounced. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> KNOCK ON DOOR </ln>
        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Come in. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> DOOR OPENS AND SHUTS </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Good evening, sir. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> You, uh-- You received my note? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Yes, indeed. Come in, won't you, and sit down? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> KING WALKS TO CHAIR AND SITS BEHIND-- </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> This is my friend and colleague, <mention ref="#watson">Dr.
                Watson </mention>. You may say anything before him that you can say to me. Whom have
            I the honor to address? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> You may address me as, er, Count Von Kramm. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> How do you do, sir? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> You must excuse this mask that I wear. The august person who
            employs me wishes his agent to be unknown to you, and I may confess at once that the
            title by which I have just called myself is not exactly my own. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> I was well aware of that fact, sir. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> You see, <mention ref="#holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>, the matter
            I am about to discuss implicates the great House of Ormstein, hereditary kings of
            Bohemia. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> That had not escaped me either, sir. In fact, if you will
            state your case, I shall be better able to advise you -- your Majesty. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker>
            <expression> ASTONISHED) How--? How did you--? (DECISIVELY </expression> Yes. Yes, I am
            the King. Why should I attempt to conceal it? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Why, indeed? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> I shall remove the mask. <expression> BEAT </expression> There.
                <mention ref="#holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>, I have traveled incognito from Prague
            for the express purpose of consulting you. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Then, pray consult. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> Briefly, the facts are these. Some five years ago, during a
            visit to Warsaw, I made the acquaintance of the well-known adventuress, Irene Adler. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Irene Adler? We know of her, your Majesty. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Look her up in the index for me, will you, <mention
                ref="#watson">Watson </mention>? It's right beside you on the desk there. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> I imagined that her name would not be unfamiliar to you. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> SHUFFLE OF PAPERS ... IN AGREEMENT WITH FOLLOWING-- </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Here we are, here we are. <expression> READS) "A. Abrahams,
                Actongreen (Hatchet Murders </expression>, Adler--" Adler. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Splendid. Hand me the file, old chap. Thank you. Mm hm!
                <expression> READS AND MUSES) "Irene Adler. Born in New Jersey in the United States
                of America in Eighteen Fifty-Eight. Contralto." Mm hm. "Prima donna, Imperial Opera
                of Warsaw." Oh. "Retired from operatic stage. Living in London." Quite so. And
                here's a recent notation -- uh huh. (TO KING </expression> Your Majesty, as I
            understand, became entangled with this young person, wrote her some compromising letters
            and is now desirous of getting those letters back. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker>
            <expression> AMAZED </expression> Precisely so. But how could--? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Was there a secret marriage? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> None. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> No legal papers or certificates? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> Er, no. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Then I fail to follow, your Majesty. If this young lady should
            produce her letters for blackmailing purposes, how is she to prove their authenticity? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> There is the handwriting. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> That could be a forgery, your Majesty. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> But it was private note-paper. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Stolen. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> My own seal. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Imitated. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> My photograph. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Bought. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> But - we were both in the photograph. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Oh, dear me. Yes, that's very bad. Your Majesty has indeed
            committed an indiscretion. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Did you inscribe this photograph, your Majesty? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> Yes, <mention ref="#watson">Dr. Watson </mention>, I am afraid I
            did. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>
            <expression> MUMBLES </expression> Good gracious me. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker>
            <mention ref="#holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>, it must be recovered. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Perhaps if you were to pay enough, the photograph might be
            bought. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> She refuses to sell. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Stolen, then. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> Five attempts have been made. Twice burglars in my pay ransacked
            her house. Once we diverted her luggage when she traveled. Twice she has been waylaid.
            There has been no result. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Oh, dear, it's quite a pretty little problem. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> It is a deadly serious one to me. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Your Majesty, what does Miss Adler intend to do with the
            photograph? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> To ruin me. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> How, sir? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> Well, I am about to be married to the second daughter of the
            King of Scandinavia. She is the [very] soul of delicacy. A shadow of a doubt as to my
            conduct would bring the matter to an end. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> And Irene Adler threatens to send the photograph to your
            fianc矇e, I suppose? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> Yes, and she will do it. Rather than let me marry another woman,
            there are no lengths to which she would not go. None. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Are you sure that she hasn't already sent it, your Majesty? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> I am sure. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> And why? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> She said she would send it on the day my betrothal is publicly
            announced. That day will be next Monday. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Splendid! Then we still have three days. Your Majesty will, of
            course, stay in London for the present? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> Yes, certainly. You will find me at the Langham Hotel,
            registered as Count Von Kramm. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Just two questions before you leave. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> What are they? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Is the photograph large or small? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> Quite large. And it was in a heavy frame. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> I see. And what is Irene Adler's London address, please? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> Briony Lodge, Serpentine Avenue, St. John's Wood. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Thank you, your Majesty. Good night, and I trust that we shall
            soon have some good news for you. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker>
            <expression> RISES</expression> I am placing all my hopes in you, <mention ref="#holmes"
                >Mr. Holmes</mention>. <expression>MOVING OFF </expression> Good night. Good night,
                <mention ref="#watson">Dr. Watson </mention>. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Good night, your Majesty. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> DOOR OPENS AND SHUTS </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Fascinating problem, Holmes. I wish I could help you with it. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> You can, my dear chap. I shall be glad of your company. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> What's our first move, Holmes? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> A good night's rest. We'll meet here at ten o'clock tomorrow
            morning. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> And then? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Then, my dear fellow, we will see what we can find out about
            Miss Irene Adler, late of the Warsaw Imperial Opera Company and at present residing at
            Briony Lodge, Serpentine Avenue, St. John's Wood. </ln>

        <music> BRIDGE </music>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Well, Holmes, I guess the examination of Briony Lodge didn't
            prove very illuminating. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> No. A bijou residence that represents the essence of dignified
            suburbia, but tells us very little about the owner. I think a visit to the local public
            house might prove more instructive. Come on, old chap. I see the door of the Coach and
            Horse is inviting us from across the road. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> TWO PAIRS OF FOOTSTEPS ON COBBLESTONE </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Well, our disguises shouldn't cause any suspicion. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> [That's why] I suggested them. In the character of a couple of
            stable hands, I felt that we might inspire confidence. This is a horsy neighborhood, and
            there's a wonderful sympathy and freemasonry among their fraternity. Here we are. Better
            let me do most of the talking. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Yes, I will. I'm sure that your accent will be more convincing
            than mine. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Let's go in, shall we? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> PUB DOOR OPENS AND SHUTS ... PUB BACKGROUND; PIANO </ln>

        <ln><speaker>BARTENDER</speaker> Well, what'll it be, mateys? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>
            <expression> COCKNEY </expression> 'Alf a bowl of malt, please. 'Ow 'bout you, Charley? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>
            <expression> COCKNEY </expression> I'll have the same. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>BARTENDER</speaker> Two half of old and mild. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> PUB BACKGROUND AND PIANO FILLS PAUSE ... THEN DRINKS ARE SET
            DOWN <expression> AND PIANO OUT </expression> BEHIND-- </ln>

        <ln><speaker>BARTENDER</speaker> Here we are, mateys. Here. That'll be a tenner. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>
            <expression> COCKNEY </expression> Have a drink wiv us, governor? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>BARTENDER</speaker> Don't mind if I do. I'll have a Guinness. You blokes new
            around here? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>
            <expression> COCKNEY </expression> Oh, yes. We just come over from Clapham. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>BARTENDER</speaker> Clapham, eh? Well, here's looking at you. <expression>
                DRINKS, EXHALES </expression> You hunting for jobs? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>
            <expression> COCKNEY </expression> Yes, that's right. We was told that Miss Adler across
            at Briony Lodge needed a new coachman and groom. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>BARTENDER</speaker> Well, it's the first I've heard of it -- but it might be
            true. Have you been over there to ask? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>
            <expression> COCKNEY </expression> No, not yet. We thought we'd find out something about
            the old girl first. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>BARTENDER</speaker>
            <expression> CHUCKLES </expression> She ain't no old girl, matey. She's the prettiest
            young thing you ever saw under a bonnet, and that's a fact. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>
            <expression> COCKNEY </expression> You know her, governor? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>BARTENDER</speaker> Yeah, of course I know her. Used to drive her carriage, I
            did, afore I come to work here. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>
            <expression> COCKNEY </expression> Oh. What's she like? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>BARTENDER</speaker> Well, as nice a little lady as you'll find, chum. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>
            <expression> COCKNEY </expression> Work you hard? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>BARTENDER</speaker> No. No, no. She lives quiet, like. Goes out singing at
            concerts once in a while. Rest of the time, it's money for gin. She goes out for a drive
            in the park every day at five and comes back to dinner at six-thirty. Rest of the time's
            your own. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>
            <expression> COCKNEY </expression> Oh, she ain't married, you say? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>BARTENDER</speaker> No, no. But she's got a bloke what comes to see her all the
            time. He's a barrister; nice gentleman. Mr. Geoffrey Norton is his name. Good looking
            fella; wouldn't be surprised to see 'em get spliced. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>
            <expression> COCKNEY) Sounds like a nice, cushy job to me. (TO WATSON) Come on, Charley,
                let's get over to the house and see what's what. (TO BARTENDER </expression> Much
            obliged to you, chum. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>BARTENDER</speaker> Good luck, mateys. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>
            <expression> COCKNEY </expression> Good night. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>BARTENDER</speaker> And thanks for the Guinness! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> PUB DOOR OPENS AND SHUTS ... PUB BACKGROUND OUT </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> What's our next move, Holmes? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Let's stroll back to Briony Lodge, shall we? I'm undecided
            whether to continue my investigations there or to try and find out something about Mr.
            Geoffrey Norton, the barrister. If he is just her lawyer and nothing else, it's more
            than likely that she's entrusted the photograph to his safekeeping. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Hello, there's a cab waiting outside Miss Adler's house. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Hurry, <mention ref="#watson">Watson </mention>. It may be Mr.
            Norton's. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> THEIR HURRIED FOOTSTEPS TO THE FRONT GATE </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>
            <expression> LOW </expression> Here we are at the gate. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>
            <expression> LOW </expression> Yes! And here comes a man hurrying down the pathway.
            Quick -- behind this post. Listen! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> NORTON'S FOOTSTEPS RUN TO CAB </ln>

        <ln><speaker>1ST CABMAN</speaker> Where to now, Mr. Norton? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>NORTON</speaker> Drive like the devil! First to Gross and Hankey's in Regent
            Street, and then to the Church of St. Monica in the Edgeware Road. Half a sovereign if
            you do it in twenty minutes! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>1ST CABMAN</speaker> Right you are, Mr. Norton! Hop in! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> NORTON CLIMBS IN ... CAB DOOR SHUTS </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>
            <expression> LOW </expression> Try and signal a cab, <mention ref="#watson">Watson
            </mention>! We must follow him! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> CAB DRIVES DOWN ROAD </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Here comes one! No, no, it isn't. It's a private carriage. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Miss Adler's, no doubt! <expression> LOW </expression> Here
            she comes down the pathway. Back again behind the post, <mention ref="#watson">Watson
            </mention>! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> ADLER'S FOOTSTEPS RUNNING TOWARD CARRIAGE </ln>

        <ln><speaker>COACHMAN</speaker> Where to, Miss Adler? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ADLER</speaker> The Church of St. Monica, John, and half a sovereign if you
            reach it in twenty minutes. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> CARRIAGE DOOR SHUTS ... CARRIAGE DRIVES DOWN ROAD </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> The game's afoot! Quick, we must get a cab and follow them! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Here comes a hansom! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> HANSOM CAB PULLS UP ... THEN STOPS BEHIND-- </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>
            <expression> CALLS </expression> Cabby! Hey, hey, cabby! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>2ND CABMAN</speaker>
            <expression> SKEPTICAL </expression> Have you blokes got enough money to take a cab? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Here's half a sovereign for you, my man! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>2ND CABMAN</speaker> Right you are! Where to, governor? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> The Church of St. Monica in the Edgeware Road, and another
            half sovereign for you if you get us there in twenty minutes! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> CAB DOOR SHUTS ... CAB DRIVES DOWN ROAD </ln>

        <music> CURTAIN </music>

        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker> We'll hear the rest of Dr. <mention ref="#watson">Watson
            </mention>'s story in just a second, but let me tell you something. If you're going to
            have chicken for dinner tomorrow night or - or any night, don't forget to serve that
            chicken with Petri California Sauterne. Believe me, Petri Sauterne is just about the
            last word in white wines. It's beautifully golden in color, it's delicate and intriguing
            in flavor and it's just-- Well, you taste it and see for yourself. If you want a
            delicious white wine, you certainly want Petri Sauterne. <expression> TO WATSON
            </expression> Well, doctor, again you broke off your story at the most exciting point.
            Did you and <mention ref="#holmes">Sherlock Holmes </mention> reach that church inside
            the twenty minutes? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Yes, Mr. Bartell, we did, but the other carriages were there
            before us. Holmes went into the church after telling me to guard the outside. I must
            have waited for ten minutes or more before Mr. Geoffrey Norton and Miss Adler came out,
            spoke a few words to each other and then left -- then and there, in their separate
            conveyances. A moment later, Holmes -- still dressed as a stable hand -- came striding
            out of the church and down the steps towards me. He was obviously very excited.
                <expression> FADES OUT </expression>
        </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>
            <expression> FADES IN </expression>
            <mention ref="#watson">Watson </mention>! <mention ref="#watson">Watson </mention>, have
            they left? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Yes, in separate cabs. I overheard him say that he was going
            back to his office. And she said, "I shall drive out in the park at five o'clock, as
            usual." </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Splendid. Then come on -- we can return to Baker Street. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> THEIR FOOTSTEPS TO CAB, DURING FOLLOWING-- </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> What happened inside the church, Holmes? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> They were married. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Married?! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Of course. The ceremony would have been illegal if performed
            after noon. That accounted for their wild dash to the church. Jump into the cab, old
            fellow. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>2ND CABMAN</speaker> Where to now, governor? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Two Twenty-One B, Baker Street. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> CAB DOOR OPENS ... HOLMES AND WATSON CLIMB IN ... CAB DOOR
            SHUTS ... CAB DRIVES DOWN ROAD, CONTINUES IN BACKGROUND </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Oh, so they got married, eh? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Yes. And it may amuse you to know that I acted as witness at
            the ceremony. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> You did? But how did that happen? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>
            <expression> LAUGHS </expression> Their own witness had failed to appear and I was
            dragged into the breach. The bride gave me this sovereign as a memento. I, uh, think
            I'll wear it on my watch-chain in memory of the occasion. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> What an amazing situation. Things begin to look better for the
            king, don't they? Now that she's Mrs. Norton, the chances are that she won't want to
            expose his Majesty, after all. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> I hope so, <mention ref="#watson">Watson </mention>, I hope
            so. But we can't afford to take any chances. I think the time is ripe for us to come to
            closer grips with the lady! </ln>

        <music> BRIDGE </music>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Well, <mention ref="#holmes">Holmes </mention>, now that we've
            eaten, perhaps you'll tell me your plan. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> With pleasure, my dear fellow -- and while I'm so doing, I'll
            proceed with applying the makeup for my new disguise. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>
            <expression> AMUSED </expression> Another disguise? What's it to be this time? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> I think the character and appearance of an amiable,
            simple-minded Nonconformist clergyman would be the most suited to my plan for entering
            Miss Adler's house. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> You're going to try and enter, then? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> I must, my dear fellow. I'm sure the photograph is there. Miss
            Adler -- or, rather, Mrs. Norton -- will return from her drive in the park at
            six-thirty. We must be at Briony Lodge to meet her. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> And what then? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> You must leave that to me. I've already made my arrangements.
            There is only one point on which I must insist -- you must not interfere, come what may.
            You understand? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> I'm to remain neutral? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Yes. There will be some small unpleasantness. Don't join in.
            It will end in my being conveyed into the house. As soon as I am able to, I shall open
            one of the windows. You are to watch from outside. When I raise my hand, you will throw
            an object -- that I shall give you -- through the window and, at the same time, cry
            "Fire!" You follow me? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Entirely. But what am I to throw? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Oh, it's nothing very formidable. Here it is. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Huh. Looks like a great big cigar. What is it? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> An ordinary plumber's smoke-rocket, fitted with a cap at
            either end to make it self-lighting. Your task is confined to throwing it through the
            window. When you raise the cry of fire, it will be taken up by quite a number of people.
            You may then walk to the end of the street, and I'll rejoin you in ten minutes. I hope
            I've made myself clear. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Perfectly. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Good. And now, old fellow, as soon as I've donned my clerical
            attire, let's be on our way. There's no time to be lost. </ln>

        <music> BRIDGE </music>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> It's nearly six-thirty, <mention ref="#holmes">Holmes
            </mention>. We've been pacing up and down in front of her house for half an hour now. I
            hope she does come back. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> I'm sure she will. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> There seem to be a lot of loafers hanging around her gate. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> All part of my conspiracy, old chap. You'll see them play
            their parts in a few minutes. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> You still think the photograph is inside the house? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Yes. It's most unlikely that she carries it about with her.
            Remember, the king told us it was a large, framed picture. And also remember that she
            planned to use it within a few days. It must be where she can lay her hands on it. It
            must be inside her house. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> But her house has been burgled. Twice. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Oh, psh! They didn't know how to look. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> How will you look? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> I won't. I'll get her to show me. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Oh, she'll refuse. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> She won't be able to-- </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> CARRIAGE APPROACHES </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Shh! Here comes the carriage now. Remember, <mention
                ref="#watson">Watson </mention> -- carry out my orders to the letter. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>
            <expression> MOVING OFF </expression> You can trust me. Good luck. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> CARRIAGE ROLLS TO A STOP </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ALFIE</speaker>
            <expression> SARCASTIC </expression> Blimey! 'Ere comes the Duchess of Tiddlywinks! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> CROWD LAUGHS ... BUZZES IN BACKGROUND </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ALFIE</speaker> Let's put out a carpet; she might get her tootsies wet! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>PAT</speaker> Awwww, put a sock in it, Alfie! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HATTIE</speaker> Leave him alone! She's no better than she ought to be! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> CROWD JEERS </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ADLER</speaker> Please, please -- let me through! I live here! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ALFIE</speaker> Well, ain't that nice! We'll all come in and have a cup of
            cocoa! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> CROWD JEERS AND LAUGHS ... GROWS INCREASINGLY UNRULY IN
            BACKGROUND </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>
            <expression> AS THE CLERGYMAN </expression> Move out of the way, please, and let the
            lady through. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HATTIE</speaker> Mind your own business! Just 'cause your collar's turned the
            wrong way round, you can't spoil our fun! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ALFIE</speaker> That's right, Hattie! Keep your nose out of it, parson! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HATTIE</speaker> Stop shovin', will ya? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ADLER</speaker> Please, please, don't fight about it! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> I'll - I'll tell you what-- <expression> HAUGHTY </expression>
            Stop molesting the lady, please! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ALFIE</speaker> Do ya? Then how would you like a biff on the nose, Mr.
            Clergyman? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> CROWD JEERS ... ALFIE PUNCHES THE CLERGYMAN WHO FALLS TO THE
            GROUND ... CROWD REACTS ... ALFIE RUNS AWAY ... CROWD DISPERSES BEHIND-- </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ADLER</speaker>
            <expression> DISTRAUGHT </expression> Oh, he hit the poor man! And then he ran away, the
            coward! Is the clergyman badly hurt? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ERNIE</speaker> He hit his head, ma'am, as he fell. If you asks me, he's hurt
            bad. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>BERT</speaker> He's bleedin' something terrible. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ERNIE</speaker> Can we bring him in, mum? He can't lie here in the street. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ADLER</speaker> Oh, why, of course. Bring him in. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ERNIE</speaker> Right you are, mum. Here, Bert-- </ln>

        <ln><speaker>BERT</speaker> Righto. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ERNIE</speaker> --give us a hand. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> MEN GRUNT AS THEY LIFT BODY AND CARRY IT INTO THE HOUSE </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HATTIE</speaker>
            <expression> SADLY </expression> Coo. Poor fella. 'Joo see what happened to him, mister? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Yes, I saw, my good woman. A very convincing demonstration. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HATTIE</speaker>
            <expression> DEFENSIVE </expression> Whatcha mean? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>
            <expression> LOW </expression> Weren't you paid by, uh, a certain gentleman for this
            performance? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HATTIE</speaker>
            <expression> DROPS HER ACT </expression> Ohhh -- you knows about it, too. You must be a
            friend of Mr. <mention ref="#holmes">Sherlock Holmes </mention>. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Yes, I am. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HATTIE</speaker> A nice gentleman. He give us five bob apiece for tonight's
            work. We ain't through yet, though. We gotta start yelling "Fire" when somebody tells
            us. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> I'm that somebody, my dear lady. There's <mention
                ref="#holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention> now. He's inside the house! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HATTIE</speaker> Yes! He's opening a window! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Now he's raising his hand -- that's my signal. Now, to throw
            the rocket! <expression> GRUNTS WITH EFFORT) Ah! There we are. (YELLS </expression>
            Fire! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> CROWD STARTS YELLING "FIRE! FIRE!" </ln>

        <music> BRIDGE </music>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> HOLMES' BRISK FOOTSTEPS APPROACH </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Holmes -- there you are! You - you have the photograph? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> No, but I know where it is. She showed me, as I told you she
            would. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Well, I'm still in the dark. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> There's no mystery, old chap. When my accomplices started the
            row in the street, I had a little moist red paint in my hand. My good friend Alfie
            pretended to strike me; I clapped my hand to my head and fell down. It's an old trick. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Yes, I understand that, but how did my throwing the rocket
            help you? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> It was all-important, my dear fellow. When a woman thinks her
            house is on fire, her instinct is at once to rush for the thing that she values most. A
            married woman grabs her baby; an unmarried one reaches for her jewel-box. In this case,
            of course, it was the photograph. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Where was it? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> In a recess in the living room, just above the right-hand
            bell-pull. I caught a glimpse of it as she drew it out. When I made it known that the
            fire was a false alarm, she replaced the photograph. As soon as I was able to, I advised
            her that I was feeling well enough to leave. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> You didn't take the photograph, then. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> No, I felt that over-precipitance at this stage might ruin
            everything. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> What do we do now? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Drive to the Langham Hotel and inform his Majesty of what has
            happened. Then return with him here. And after that, my dear chap, the case will be
            ended! </ln>

        <music> BRIDGE </music>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> CAB PULLS TO A STOP </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> This is Briony Lodge, your Majesty. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> I am all impatience. You are certain the photograph will still
            be there, <mention ref="#holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> I have every reason to believe so, your Majesty. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> THE THREE CLIMB OUT OF THE CAB AND WALK TO FRONT DOOR, DURING
            FOLLOWING-- </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> I must confess, this is going to be something of an ordeal. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Then I suggest that you let me do the talking, your Majesty. I
            think I know how to handle the lady. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> KNOCKS ON FRONT DOOR ... DOOR OPENS </ln>

        <ln><speaker>MAID</speaker>
            <mention ref="#holmes">Mr. Sherlock Holmes </mention>, I believe? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>
            <expression> MILDLY SURPRISED </expression> Yes. I am <mention ref="#holmes">Mr. Holmes
            </mention>. But - how did you know? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>MAID</speaker> My mistress told me you would be likely to call. She's left for
            the Continent with her husband. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> You mean she's left England? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>MAID</speaker> Never to return. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker>
            <expression> DISTRESSED </expression> Then the papers -- and the photograph? Oh, all is
            lost! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> We'll soon see. Follow me. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> THEIR HURRIED FOOTSTEPS INTO THE HOUSE </ln>

        <ln><speaker>MAID</speaker>
            <expression> SLIGHTLY MOCKING </expression> She said you'd be looking for something. I
            hope you find it! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> This was the bell-rope. Sliding panel behind it. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> HOLMES TAPS SEVERAL TIMES ON THE WALL </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Uh huh. Here it is. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> PANEL SLIDES OPEN </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker>
            <expression> BEAT </expression> Is - is the photograph there, <mention ref="#holmes">Mr.
                Holmes </mention>? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>
            <expression> UNHAPPY </expression> There is a photograph, your Majesty. But it's, um, a
            photograph of the lady alone. Here's a letter -- and it's addressed to me. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>SOUND</speaker> ENVELOPE TORN OPEN, LETTER UNFOLDED </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> What does it say, <mention ref="#holmes">Holmes </mention>? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>
            <expression> READS </expression> "My dear <mention ref="#holmes">Mr. Sherlock Holmes
            </mention>. You really did it very well. Until after the fire alarm, I had no suspicion.
            But then, when I realized how I had betrayed myself, I began to think. I had been warned
            that if the King employed an agent he would certainly employ you. May I congratulate you
            on your disguise as a dear, old clergyman." </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>
            <expression> AMUSED </expression> Great Scott! She was much more clever than you
            thought, <mention ref="#holmes">Holmes </mention>! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker>
            <expression> IMPATIENT </expression> Ja, ja, go on. What else does it say? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>
            <expression> CLEARS THROAT, READS </expression> "My husband and I both thought that the
            best recourse was flight, so you will find the nest empty. As to the photograph of the
            King and myself, his Majesty may rest in peace." <expression>TO HIMSELF</expression> Oh,
            thank goodness for that. <expression>READS</expression> "I love and am loved by a better
            man than he. I leave another photograph, however, that he might care to possess; and I
            remain, dear <mention ref="#holmes">Mr. Sherlock Holmes</mention> , very truly yours,
            Irene Norton, ne Adler." <expression>IMPRESSED, EXCITED</expression>What a woman,
                <mention ref="#watson">Watson </mention>; what a woman; what a magnificent woman!
            She fooled me completely! <expression>CATCHES HIMSELF </expression> But-- Oh. I, uh--
            I'm sorry, your Majesty, I - I've been unable to bring your business to a more
            successful conclusion. </ln>
        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> On the contrary, my dear sir. Nothing could be more successful.
            I know that Irene's word is inviolate. The incriminating photograph is now as safe as if
            it were in the fire. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Well, I'm glad to hear your Majesty say so. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> I am immensely indebted to you. Pray tell me in what way I can
            reward you. Uh, this - this beryl ring that I wear. I - I should be proud to-- </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Your Majesty has something that I should value even more
            highly. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> You have but to name it. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> This photograph, sir. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>KING</speaker> Irene's photograph? But certainly. However, you must let me give
            you something more substantial. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker> Oh no, no, no, your Majesty. This is something I shall
            treasure all my life. This and a golden sovereign I received from the lady's hand. They
            will remind me that I was once tricked by a woman! A woman that I shall never forget. </ln>

        <music> CURTAIN </music>

        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker> Gee, doctor, what a woman, that Miss Adler. Or should I say
            Mrs. Norton. <expression> SIGHS </expression> That's the kind of woman I could really go
            for. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Yes, I believe you could. Just between ourselves, you know, I
            sort of -- ahem -- sort of could go for her meself. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker> She was intelligent. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> She was rich. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker> And beautiful. That's the kind of woman you want sitting
            next to you in front of a cozy fire on a nippy fall night. Just the three of you. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> The three of you? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker> Mm hm. You. She. And a glass of Petri Port. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>
            <expression> LAUGHS </expression> Mr. Bartell--! </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker> Well, why not? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>
            <expression> CHUCKLES </expression> Gracious. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker> Petri California Port is some wine! Boy, that Petri family
            really knows how to make good wine, all right. And no wonder. Look at all the experience
            they've had. Ever since they started the Petri business, way back in the eighteen
            hundreds, the Petri family has handed down from father to son -- from father to son --
            the art of selecting perfect, sun-ripened California grapes and making them into clear,
            fragrant, delicious wine. Those letters -- P-E-T-R-I -- on the label of every bottle of
            Petri wine are the personal assurance of the Petri family that every drop of wine in
            that bottle is good wine. It's got to be! Because Petri took time to bring you good
            wine. <expression> TO WATSON </expression> Well, <mention ref="#watson">Dr. Watson
            </mention>, that was a great story you told us tonight. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> I thought you'd like it, Mr. Bartell. That's why I plan to
            tell you a sequel to it next week. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker> A sequel? Say, that sounds exciting, doctor. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker> Oh, I think you'll find it proves to be, Mr. Bartell. It's a
            story that takes place twenty years after tonight's adventure. Once again, the principal
            part is played by a woman. Only in this case, it isn't Irene Adler. It's her daughter.
                <expression> BEAT </expression> Oh, and, uh, now, Mr. Bartell, before I go I want to
            remind our listeners that they owe a real debt of gratitude to the Selective Service
            Boards in their communities. At this moment, the Selective Service Boards are working
            harder than ever, making sure that every returning veteran knows his rights and
            privileges. And the Boards are helping him take full advantage of those rights and
            privileges. They're helping our veterans get jobs. Our Selective Service Boards deserve
            our sincere thanks and they deserve our cooperation. They have done -- and they are
            doing -- a splendid job. </ln>

        <music> THEME ... THEN UNDER-- </music>

        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker> Tonight's <mention ref="#holmes">Sherlock Holmes </mention>
            adventure was written by Denis Green and Anthony Boucher, and is an adaptation of the
            Sir Arthur Conan Doyle story "A Scandal in Bohemia." Music is by Dean Fosler. Mr.
            Rathbone appears through the courtesy of Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer and Mr. Bruce through the
            courtesy of Universal Pictures, where they are now starring in the <mention
                ref="#holmes">Sherlock Holmes </mention> series. </ln>

        <ln> The Petri Wine Company of San Francisco, California invites you to tune in again next
            week -- same time, same station. "<mention ref="#holmes">Sherlock Holmes </mention>"
            comes to you from our Hollywood studios. </ln>

        <music> OUT </music>

        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker> This is Harry Bartell saying "Good night" for the Petri
            family. <expression> PAUSE </expression> For a solid hour of exciting mystery-dramas,
            listen every Monday on most of these same stations at eight o'clock to "Bulldog
            Drummond," followed immediately by "<mention ref="#holmes">Sherlock Holmes </mention>." </ln>

        <ln><speaker>MUT ANNCR</speaker> This is the Mutual Broadcasting System. </ln>
    </scene>
</xml>
