<?xml-model href="../sherlock.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
    <metadata>
        <series>Series: Sherlock Holmes</series>
        <show>Show: The Case of the Dead Adventuress</show>
        <date when="1945-02-05">Date: Feb 05 1945</date>

        <author>by <person xml:id="green">Denis Green</person> and <person xml:id="taylor">Bruce
                Taylor</person></author>
        
        <note> (Script transcribed courtesy of Arizona TheatreWorks)</note>

        <castList>cast <cast xml:id="holmes">Sherlock Holmes</cast>
            <cast xml:id="watson">Dr. Watson</cast>
            <cast xml:id="charel">Inspector Charel</cast>
            <cast xml:id="prefect">Prefect of Police</cast>
            <cast xml:id="shipton">Hon. Reginald Shipton</cast>
            <cast xml:id="boncourt">Duc De Boncourt</cast>
            <cast xml:id="vorvey">Yvette Corvey</cast>
            <cast xml:id="borel">Henri Borel</cast>
            <cast xml:id="gendarme">Gendarme</cast></castList>


       
    </metadata>
    <script>
        <ln><speaker>Forman</speaker>Petri Wine brings you...</ln>

        <ln><music>Theme...Fade on Cue</music></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Forman</speaker>Basil Rathbone and Nigel Bruce in the new adventures on
                <mention ref="holmes">Sherlock Holmes</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><music>Theme...Full Finish</music></ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Insert opening commercial</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Forman</speaker>And now let's look in on the genial doctor<mention ref="watson"
                > Watson</mention>, and see what a story he has waiting for us. Good evening,
            Doctor.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>'Evening, Mr. Forman. Take you coat off...and your scarf...and
            your gloves...and your goloshes...That's it. <stageDirect>Chuckling</stageDirect> It's
            certainly raining cats and dogs tonight. Come and sit by the fire and warm yourself
            up.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Forman</speaker>Thank you Doctor. All set for tonight's story?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>Yes, I'm "all set," as you say.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Forman</speaker>Last week you told us your adventure took place in the south of
            France.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>Yes, Mr. Forman, and if you can imagine yourself basking in the
            sunshine of the Riviera with<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention> and myself in the
            early nineteen-hundreds, perhaps it'll help you forget what a beastly night it is
            outside.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Forman</speaker>I've forgotten that already, Doctor. How did your story
            begin?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>Simple enough.<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention> and I
            were staying in Nice, when we were visited at our hotel by a young Englishman, the
            Honourable Reginald Shipton. The boy was in serious trouble and had come to<mention
                ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention> for help.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Forman</speaker>And I'm sure he got it.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>He did, though in giving it,<mention ref="holmes">
                Holmes</mention> was arrested for murder!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Forman</speaker>For murder?! Say, Doctor, how did a thing like that happen to
            the great <mention ref="holmes">Sherlock Holmes</mention>?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>That's just what I'm going to tell you. The boy had become
            involved with a...a rather notorious French lady-Madame Corvey. She was much older than
            he, though I must admit she was a glamorous creature, and the boy's infatuation was
            understandable...at least <stageDirect>chuckling</stageDirect> I found it so.
            Unfortunately, he had given the lady an exquisite diamond and sapphire necklace [sic]
            that was a family heirloom...although he overlooked the fact that he had not yet
            inherited it.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Forman</speaker>Then of course he had no right to make the gift?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>Of course he hadn't...and when his father, Lord Shipton,
            learned what had happened he threatened to disinherit him unless he got the necklace
            back...and so, the boy came to Homes with his problem. At first, the great man tried the
            ordinary methods of handling the case. He approached Madame Corvey directly and was told
            to mind his own business. He tried persuasion, deception...he even went to the police,
            but to no avail. Finally, one night...he disappeared. I was frantic, because I knew he
            was in danger, and so I got in touch with the police. Within half an hour Inspector
            Charel telephoned me to come over to Madame Corvey's villa at once-that<mention
                ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention> was in serious trouble.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Forman</speaker>And of course you rushed over there.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>As fast as a carriage would carry me. My fears increased as I
            drew up at the villa and saw a cordon of police guarding the building. But as I got
            inside and saw my old friend, a cold terror struck at my heart. There he was in the
            library, Madame Corvey lying at his feet, with her throat slashed...and in<mention
                ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>'s hand was a bloodstained dagger! You can imagine
            what <mention ref="charel">Monsieur Charel</mention>, the chief of police, <stageDirect>fading</stageDirect> said as I
            came in...</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker><stageDirect>About forty-five...cold...precise...French
                accent</stageDirect> <mention ref="watson">Dr. Watson</mention>...Your famous friend has made his last mistake. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>Great Heavens! What's going on.
                <stageDirect>Urgently</stageDirect><mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>! Tell
            me!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Madame Corvey has been murdered,<mention ref="watson">
                Watson</mention>, and unfortunately our friend, <mention ref="charel">Monsieur Charel</mention>, seems to be under
            the impression that I killed her.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>But that's utterly ridiculous!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>Is it? Then how do you account for the fact when we came here
            just now, <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention> was standing here alone with a
            corpse?</ln>
        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker><stageDirect>Exasperated</stageDirect> Well,<mention
                ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>...Why don't you explain what happened?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>I've already done so but <mention ref="charel">Monsieur Charel</mention> doesn't seem to
            believe me. However...for your benefit...I came back here to try and have another talk
            with Madame Corvey, I found the front door open and walked in...to discover the safe
            looted, and its owner stabbed to death. I picked up the dagger from the floor to examine
            it, and as I did so, <mention ref="charel">Monsieur Charel</mention> and police came in.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>I should have thought a great detective like you,
                <mention ref="holmes">Monsieur Holmes</mention>, could have thought up a more
            ingenious lie than that. <stageDirect>Calling in French</stageDirect> Take him away to
            the suretee [ Monsieursic]!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Gendarme</speaker><stageDirect>In French</stageDirect> Come along,
            <mention ref="holmes"> Monsieur</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker><stageDirect>hotly</stageDirect> Tell that policeman to take
            his hands off you,<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>!</ln>
        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>But I haven't the right to, <mention ref="watson">my dear chap</mention>. You see, just before
            you arrived, <mention ref="charel">Monsieur Charel</mention> had <stageDirect>fading</stageDirect> arrested me for
            murder.</ln>
        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>And there my old friend was, spending the night in custody. </ln>
        <ln><speaker>Forman</speaker>And I suppose you stayed there right with him, Doctor.</ln>
        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>Not for long, Mr. Forman. He...He-eh-gave me a little job to
            do. Let me tell you just what happened. The next morning found us in the office of the
            Prefect of Police. There we were...<mention ref="holmes">Holmes</mention> and I...Inspector Charel...and the various
            witnesses connected with the case. It was a strange sight as<mention ref="holmes">
                Holmes</mention> stood there <stageDirect>fading</stageDirect> defending
            himself...</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Fade in babble of voices. Raps of gavel.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>Quiet! Quiet!</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Babble of voices subsiding.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker><stageDirect>Elderly, accent. Off a little, on slight
            echo</stageDirect> <mention ref="holmes"> Monsieur Sherlock Holmes</mention> is an
            eminent visitor to our country. That is why this preliminary investigation is being held
            in private. Thought he has been caught under extremely incriminating circumstances, let
            us at least extend him the courtesy of a fair hearing. Proceed, <mention ref="holmes"
                >Mr. Holmes</mention>. You have told us that you were brought into the case in the
            fist place at the request of the Honourable Reginald Shipton. Am I right?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Yes, <mention ref="prefect"> Monsieur Le Prefect</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>Is the honourable Reginald Shipton present?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reggie</speaker><stageDirect>Fading in...English...young</stageDirect> Here,
            <mention ref="prefect"> Monsieur Le Prefect</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>Do you corroborate the evidence so far given by
                <mention ref="holmes">Monsieur Holmes</mention>?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reggie</speaker>Yes...he's told the truth so far.
                <stageDirect>violently</stageDirect> But, if I'd known then that he was going to
            murder Madame Corvey...I'd have strangled him myself!</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Rap of gavel</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>Quiet! Please confine yourself to answering questions.</ln>

        <ln>Proceed, <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>. What was your next move?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>To meet Madame Corvey and try and reason with her.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>and how did you accomplish this aim?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>My client informed me that Madame Corvey was giving a large
            ball at her villa that night. I suggested that he take my old friend <mention
                ref="watson">Doctor Watson</mention> and myself along with him to meet the
            lady.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>And did you meet her?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Oh yes, M. Le Prefect. We arrived about eight o'clock to find a
            crowd of a hundred and fifty people or more, dancing <stageDirect>fading</stageDirect>
            to the music of a string orchestra...</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>String orchestra concluding a polka</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker><stageDirect>After music is established</stageDirect> A very
            distinguished gathering, Mr. Shipton. Madame Corvey must be extremely popular.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reggie</speaker><stageDirect>Bitterly</stageDirect> Too confoundedly popular
            for my liking, <mention ref="watson">Doctor Watson</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Orchestra finishes. Applause. Chatter of voices in B. G.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Where is Madam Corvey? I should like to meet her as soon as
            possible. These affairs are not much in my line.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker><stageDirect>Mumbling</stageDirect> I think it's rather gay, if
            you ask me.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Duc</speaker><stageDirect>Fading in. Elderly. Stupid, with an irritating
                giggle</stageDirect> Hello,</ln>

        <ln>Reginald. I was not expecting to see you here.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reggie</speaker><stageDirect>Sourly</stageDirect> I'm sorry to surprise
            you.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Duc</speaker>Won't you introduce me to your friends?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reggie</speaker>Monsieur Le Duc de Boncourt...<mention ref="holmes">Mr.
                Holmes</mention>, and <mention ref="watson">Doctor Watson</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Ad lib how d'you dos.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Duc</speaker>All here to worship at the shrine of Venus I suppose?
                <stageDirect>he thrills with revolting laughter</stageDirect> By the way, Reginald,
            I thought you had received your conge. From what Yvette told me today it seemed
            that...</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reginald</speaker><stageDirect>Interrupting brusquely</stageDirect> I'm afraid
            we're in a bit of a hurry. Good evening, <mention ref="duc"> Monsieur Le Duc.</mention></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Duc</speaker><stageDirect>Fading</stageDirect> Not jealous of me, are you, Reginald? <stageDirect>he
                laughs again</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>Pon' [sic] my soul, my boy, you were extraordinarily rude to
            him, if y'don't mind my saying so.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reginald</speaker>He's an insufferable old ass and I can't stand him. He thinks
            that because Yvette smiles at him for the moment that he's going to marry her.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>The Duc is the current favourite, I take it?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker><stageDirect>Fading in</stageDirect> Ah, <mention ref="holmes"> Monsieur
                Sherlock Holmes</mention>. How are you?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>I'm afraid I don't know you, monsieur.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>No...but I know you...and your friend <mention ref="watson"
                >Doctor Watson</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>Oh really, I don't remember meeting you, <mention ref="charel">sir</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reggie</speaker>This is <mention ref="charel">Monsieur Charel</mention>-inspector of the suretee [sic]</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Ad lib how d'you dos from Watson and Holmes.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>When distinguished rivals honour my town with their presence!
                <mention ref="holmes">Monsieur Holmes</mention>, I make it my business to recognize
            them.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>That's very flattering of you.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>Not at all. You're not here on business, I suppose.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker><stageDirect>lightly</stageDirect> Oh dear me no. On pleasure,
            monsieur. Purely on pleasure.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>Splendid. You will find Madame Corvey's parties enchanting, I'm
            sure. <stageDirect>Fading</stageDirect> Au revoir, messieurs.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>Charming fellow.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reggie</speaker>Do you think so? He's just another old fool who thinks Yvette's
            in love with him. <stageDirect>Suddenly</stageDirect> There's Yvette now. Come on...I'll
            introduce you. And then I'll get out of the way. I don't want to talk to her more than I
            have to.</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>String orchestra starting an old fashioned two-step</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reggie</speaker><stageDirect>Calling</stageDirect> Yvette!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Yvette</speaker><stageDirect>Fading in</stageDirect> <stageDirect>gay, sophisticated, charming
                Frenchwoman in the early forties</stageDirect> Reginald! 'Ow nice to see you. I did
            not know you were coming.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reggie</speaker>I changed my mind. Yvette...I want you to meet two friends of
            mine. <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention> and <mention ref="watson">Doctor
                Watson</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Yvette</speaker>Enchante, messieurs.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>How d'you do, Madame Corvey.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker><stageDirect>Audibly smitten</stageDirect> I'm extremely glad
            to meet you, Madame.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reggie</speaker>They want to talk to you privately,
                <stageDirect>fading</stageDirect> so I'll leave you.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Yvette</speaker>Reginald, you silly boy, come back 'ere! <stageDirect>After a
                moment</stageDirect> <stageDirect>with a laugh</stageDirect> He is so young, isn't he? Youth has a charm all
            of its own, messieurs...but for a woman like myself I find it a little trying...for too
            long at one time. It is more soothing to be with people my own age, like
            yourselves.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker><stageDirect>Burbling happily</stageDirect> Awfully nice of you to say so,
                Madame. But I know we're both a great deal older than you are. <stageDirect>He laughs
                rogueishly</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Yvette</speaker>Nonsense. But your friend-he has-'ow you say-the long
            face...What is the matter, Mr. 'Olmes?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Nothing , madame...except that I'd like to have a little
            business talk with you.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Yvette</speaker>Business?! With this music playing? No, no, no. Your friend
            shall dance with me.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>I shall be very proud to take you for a twirl. Madame Corvey.
                <stageDirect>Modestly</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Forgive me, Madame...and<mention ref="watson">
            Watson</mention>, <mention ref="watson">old chap</mention> but I must insist on this business talk first.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Yvette</speaker>Business! You are very tiresome...but because I like your
            friend, I will talk business with you. Come and sit over'ere....<stageDirect>After a
                pause</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>The diamond and sapphire necklace you are wearing, madame. I
            presume it's the one Lord Shipton's son gave you?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Yvette</speaker><stageDirect>Her tone changing</stageDirect> Yes. What of
            it?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>D'you mind if I examine it?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Yvette</speaker>Yes, I do-very much. What are you? A diamond buyer.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>No, I am a friend of Mr. Shipton's. He asked me to try and
            persuade you to return the necklace to him. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>Yvette</speaker>The insolent puppy! It is mine. He gave it to me-in front of
            witnesses.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>He had no right to, Madame. It did not belong to him.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Yvette</speaker>Then he is a thief...and that is no concern of mine. He made a
            gift, and I accepted it.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Would you consider...er...selling back your gift?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Yvette</speaker>No! I would not!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Are you sure? Reginald would pay a fair price for
                it...<stageDirect>meaningly [sic]</stageDirect> and it may have depreciated in value
            since you received it, you know.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Yvette</speaker><stageDirect>Angrily</stageDirect> Go away! Go away before I
            have you thrown out!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker><stageDirect>Embarrassed</stageDirect> I'm awfully sorry,
            Madame. My friend's really a....</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Yvette</speaker>Go away both of you! <stageDirect>Fading</stageDirect> You bore
            me!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker><stageDirect>After a moment</stageDirect> 'Pon my soul! Never
            seen a woman change her tune so quickly. Fascinating creature, though. If there's one
            thing I like in a woman it's spirit.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Rubbish! Madame Corvey's an adventuress.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>Why d'you say that,<mention ref="holmes">
            Holmes</mention>?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Because, although she wouldn't let me examine the necklace, I
            was able to detect that the diamonds have been replaced by imitations.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>Good land! You mean that she sold the originals?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Undoubtedly. Sold them-or kept them.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reggie</speaker><stageDirect>Fading in excitedly</stageDirect>
            <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Yes, my boy? I was just looking for you. What's wrong?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reggie</speaker>I want to leave here at once. I've just heard that Yvette's
            going to announce her engagement to the Duc de Boncourt tonight. I don't want to stay to
            hear it.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>I quite understand. Though if I were you, I would be relieved
            rather than upset by the announcement.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reggie</speaker>What did she say to you when you asked her about the necklace,
                <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Very little. But I have a feeling that you might be able to but
            it back for a reasonable sum.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reggie</speaker>But I've tried that...and she wouldn't part with it.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Try again, my dear boy. I think my little conversation with her
            tonight, might cause her to change her opinion as to its market value.</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Orchestra up, then down and out.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Fading in</stageDirect> Hubbub of voices. Rap of gavel.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>Quiet! Quiet! Pray continue <mention ref="holmes">Mr.
                Holmes</mention>. What happened next?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Early the next morning Shipton came round to see me with the
            information that he had recovered the necklace for a very reasonable sum.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>Did you tell him that the diamonds had been replaced?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>No. <mention ref="prefect"> Monsieur</mention>. I didn't.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>Why not?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>I felt that before I told him anything about Madame Corvey with
            any degree of authority, it was only fair to re-inforce my beliefs with facts.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>So what did you do?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>The obvious thing. After all, I have no official standing in
            your country, and yet I knew Madame Corvey was a criminal...or perhaps I should say-an
            adventuress. And so I decided to pay a visit to <mention ref="charel">Monsieur Charel</mention>-the head inspector of
            your local police. After my client left, <mention ref="watson">Doctor Watson</mention>
            and I went round to <mention ref="charel">Monsieur Charel</mention>'s office. <stageDirect>Fading</stageDirect> He
            seemed to be very pleased to see us...</ln>
        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>Ah, <mention ref="holmes"> Monsieur Sherlock
            Holmes</mention>...and his friend. Come in. I am very flattered that you come to see
            me.</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Holmes and Watson ad lib how d'you dos.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>Is this a business visit, messieurs, or am I to suppose that
            you come here to make my acquaintance better?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>A little of both, <mention ref="charel"> Monsieur</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>Please tell me what I can do for you?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker><mention ref="charel">Monsieur Charel</mention>, I was not [t]elling you the truth at Madame
            Corvey's party last night when I said I was there purely on pleasure.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>I was well aware of that, monsieur.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>But how could you...</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker><stageDirect>Smoothly</stageDirect>
            <mention ref="watson">Doctor Watson</mention>, very little goes on in this town that I
            am not aware of. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Perhaps you know why I was at the party?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>But of course.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>And did you know that this morning Madame Corvey parted with
            the necklace...in consideration of a cash payment?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>No, I did not know. But it is her own affair. Is your client
            satisfied with his bargain?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Perfectly...but, you see, he doesn't know that the diamonds
            have been removed and replaced with imitations. I noticed that when I was talking to
            Madame Corvey last night.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>Had you ever seen the necklace before?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>No.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>How do you know that the necklace ever was valuable? You have
            said your client is satisfied. What do you wish me to do?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>I should like you to investigate Madame Corvey.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker><stageDirect>Coldly</stageDirect> <mention ref="holmes"> Monsieur Holmes</mention>; Yvette Corvey is a
                brilliant and distinguished woman. Duels have been fought over her. Kings have paid
                homage to her. And now, because some stupid English boy has had trouble over a
                paltry necklace, you expect me to investigate her? In France, <mention ref="holmes"> Monsieur Holmes</mention>, we
                police do not work without evidence, and I think it will be good for you to remember
                that fact. <stageDirect>Fading</stageDirect> Good day, messieurs....</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Chatter of voices. Gavel. Chatter subsides.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>And then what happened, <mention ref="holmes">Monsieur
                Holmes</mention>, after you had left Inspector Charel's office?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Monsieur le Prefect, I was deeply dissatisfied. I knew in my
            own mind that Madame Corvey was guilty. and so I decided to pay her another visit.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>Why did you go alone? Your friend <mention ref="watson">Doctor
                Watson</mention> had been with you during your previous expeditions.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>I intended to burgle the safe, and I didn't want to incriminate
            my old friend in such a risky proceeding.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>You admit you went there to burgle the safe?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Yes, <mention ref="prefect"> Monsieur le Prefect</mention>. But, of course, when I got there,
            someone had rifled the safe before me-and murdered Madame Corvey.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>Please tell me exactly what happened. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>I arrived at the villa just after midnight. Perhaps I should
            explain the villa is built around a courtyard in such a way that, short of smashing one
            of the ground floor windows, there are only two ways in-a door on the street-and a door
            at the back which opens on to the beach.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>And which way had you proposed to try and enter?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>From the beach...but, as I approached from that direction, I
            noticed a light still burning in the library, and so I circled the house to investigate
            the chances of entering through the front door with the aid of a skeleton key. As I did
            so, I noticed to my surprise that the door was open a fraction. Of course...I went
            in.... </ln>

        <ln><music>sneaks in underscoring dialogue.</music></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>I tip-toed along the hallway.</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Furtive footsteps on wood</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Everything was quiet.... Suddenly I stumbled over
            something.</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Shuffle of footsteps</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>It was a body.</ln>

        <ln><music>knife chord, then down and under</music></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>I struck a match.</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Match being struck</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>It was the Duc de Boncourt. At first, I thought he was dead,
            but when I turned him over I realized he was unconscious. I decided to investigate a
            little further and so I walked towards the library....</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Footsteps on Wood</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker><stageDirect>After a pause</stageDirect> I opened the door and
            went in.</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Door open. Footsteps stop.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><music>Chord, then down.</music></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>The lights were on....and I saw Madame Corvey lying on the rug
            in front of the fire with her throat slashed, and a dagger lying beside her. The
            wall-safe near the bookcase was open...and empty. I stooped down and touched Madame
            Corvey..her body was still warm. Then I picked up the dagger-by its blade-and started to
            examine it. As I did so...I heard a rattling at the French windows leading to the
            courtyard.</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Rattling of windows, off</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Of course...it was Inspector Charel.</ln>

        <ln><music>Up strong and out cold.</music></ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Windows being wrenched open. Approaching footsteps.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker><stageDirect>Fading in excitedly</stageDirect>
            <mention ref="holmes">Sherlock Holmes</mention>! I've caught you red-handed!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Please don't wave that revolver at me, <mention ref="charel">Monsieur Charel</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>Madame Corvey! Is she...?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Yes...she's dead...murdered.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>You did it!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Don't be ridiculous!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>Then how is it that I find you along with the murdered
            woman-and with the weapon in your hand!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>It's very easily explained. I came here to...</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Running footsteps approaching.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>Who's that?...The Honourable Reginald Shipton! How did you get
            in here?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reggie</speaker><stageDirect>Fading in, excitedly</stageDirect> The door was open. I ...
                <stageDirect>Hysterically</stageDirect> Yvette! Yvette!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>I'm afraid she's been murdered, my boy.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reggie</speaker>Murdered?! But who...?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>Judge for yourself, monsieur!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reggie</speaker>Holmes!<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>, you
            filthy...</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Scuffle.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Don't be a fool! Use a little intelligence!</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Struggle increased.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reggie</speaker>Yvette's dead! You killed her!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker><stageDirect>In French</stageDirect> Take him outside.</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Scuffle subsiding.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>Monsieur<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>, before I
            telephone for your friend, <mention ref="watson">Doctor Watson</mention>, I must indulge
            in a slight formality.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>And what's that, inspector?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>I arrest you for the murder of Madame Yvette Corvey!</ln>

        <ln><music>Up strong to curtain.</music></ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Insert middle commercial</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Forman</speaker>And now, back to tonight's new <mention ref="holmes">Sherlock
                Holmes</mention> adventure. The great detective, and his old friend <mention
                ref="watson">Doctor Watson</mention>, are in the south of France where they have
            become involved in a strange case connected with a famous adventuress-Yvette
                Corvey.<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>, having failed in his preliminary
            investigations, has decided to pay a call on the lady, alone and after midnight, but in
            doing so has landed himself in serious trouble, for he has found Madame Corvey murdered
            and himself arrested for the crime. As we rejoin our story, the Prefect of Police is
                <stageDirect>fading</stageDirect> conducting an official trial....</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Chatter of voices, raps of gavel. Chatter subsides.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>Monsieur<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>, we have heard
            your evidence as to how you entered the villa and found the body of Madame Corvey. You
            realize, of course, that your story is entirely uncorroborated?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Yes, I do, <mention ref="prefect"> Monsieur le Prefect</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>You stated that you found M. le Duc de Boncourt, lying in the
            hallway, unconscious, as you entered the house.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Yes, <mention ref="prefect"> Monsieur le Prefect</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>Is the Duc de Boncourt present?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Duc</speaker><stageDirect>Fading in</stageDirect> Oui, <mention ref="prefee"> Monsieur le Prefee</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>What is your own story regarding last night's tragedy?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Duc</speaker>I had taken Yvette to the ballet. We came back about eleven
            thirty. The servants were in bed, but they had left a snack for us-some cold fowl and a
            bottle of champagne. Just before midnight, we decided to have a little more champagne
            and so I started off to the cellar. As I came into the hallway, I suddenly received a
            violent blow on the head...and I don't remember any more until the police revived
            me.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>I see. Thank you, <mention ref="duc"> Monsieur le Duc</mention>. Is the honourable Reginald
            Shipton here?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reggie</speaker><stageDirect>Fading in</stageDirect> Yes, <mention ref="prefect"> Monsieur le
            Prefect</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>What were you doing at Madame Corvey's villa last night,
            monsieur? It has already been testified that you had received your necklace
            back....</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reggie</speaker><stageDirect>In a low voice</stageDirect> I, ...I...came over
            to try and persuade her to change her mind...to throw over the Duc de Boncourt...and
            marry me. When I came to the house...The door was open...I walked in...and found poor
            Yvette murdered. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>I see. Thank you, monsieur. <stageDirect>After a
                moment</stageDirect> Inspector Charel, I cannot help but feel that you have produced
            a very inconclusive case against <mention ref="holmes"> Monsieur Sherlock
                Holmes</mention>. It seems to me that both the Duc de Boncourt and the Hon. Reginald
            Shipton had equal opportunities, and greater motive to murder Madame Corvey than he
            did.</ln>
        <ln><speaker>Duc</speaker><stageDirect>off. Excitedly</stageDirect> <mention ref="prefee"> Monsieur le Prefee</mention>! Que
            dites moi?!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Reggie</speaker>But that's ridiculous! I loved Yvette! I'd never have...</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Rap of gavel. Voices subside.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>Quiet! <stageDirect>After a moment</stageDirect> I did not say
            that you gentlemen did it. I'm saying that you both had the opportunity.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker><mention ref="prefect">Monsieur le Prefect</mention>...as I am under arrest, may I have the
            privilege of proving myself innocent?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>Mais certainment, <mention ref="holmes">monsieur</mention>...if you can.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>I think the identity of the murderer will be obvious when we
            find the jewels stolen from Madame Corvey's safe. Now the three people present at, or
            about, the time of the lady's murder-were <speaker>searched</speaker>myself-the Duc-and
            Mr. Shipton here. Am I right Inspector Charel?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>Yes, <mention ref="holmes">monsieur</mention>, and the jewels were not found-so what does that
            prove?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>One other person that had a motive for killing Madame Corvey
            was not searched-yourself, Inspector.</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Excited buzz of voices.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker><stageDirect>Angrily</stageDirect> But this is outrageous! Are
            you accusing me?</ln>


        <ln><stageDirect>Rap of gavel. Voices subside.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>Monsieur<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>, do you
            realize the significance of what you are implying?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>I do, <mention ref="prefect"> Monsieur le Prefect</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>Very well then. Proceed.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker><mention ref="charel">Monsieur Charel</mention>, you stated that the beach gate was bolted. How
            did you find that out?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>By trying it.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>From inside-or outside?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>From outside, of course.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>I don't believe you. I think that when <mention ref="watson"
                >Doctor Watson</mention> telephoned your office you suspected where I might be
            going. You hurried ahead of the gendarmes and reached the Villa several minutes before I
            did. You found the beach gate was open...you saw Madame Corvey putting her jewels away,
            as <mention ref="boncourt"> Monsieur le Duc de Boncourt</mention> started to leave the room to go the cellar. You slipped
            through the windows, signaled to Madame Corvey, who was your confederate, to be
            silent...followed the Duc into the hall and struck him from behind. Then you went back
            into the library, killed Madame Corvey, and pocketed the jewels. You started to leave
            the front way...and saw me approaching. Seeing a chance to implicate me, you left the
            door ajar...and ran out the beach way, bolting the door behind you, and waited for your
            reinforcements.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>You have convicted yourself! If you came to the villa after I
            was there-how could you have known what my movements were? </ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>I admit that this part of my case is only supposition.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>But <mention ref="holmes">Monsieur Holmes</mention>, that is
            no evidence.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>Of course it is not!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Now I'll come to my facts. <mention ref="watson">Doctor
                Watson</mention>, I wonder if you'd mind stepping forward?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker><stageDirect>fading in</stageDirect> I'm very glad to. In fact,
            I've been wondering why you haven't asked me to before,<mention ref="holmes">
                Holmes</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Will you please tell <mention ref="prefect"> Monsieur le Prefect</mention> exactly what you did
            last night after I was brought here.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>With pleasure. <stageDirect>Raising his voice
                slightly</stageDirect> <mention ref="prefect"> Monsieur le Prefect</mention>, my old friend <mention ref="holmes">Mr.
                Holmes</mention> told me to shadow Inspector Charel as soon as he left the Suretee
            [sic] last night. And that's what I did...He walked down to the waterfront and entered a
            small caf?....I watched through the window and saw him give a package to a rough-looking
            sailor-and a few minutes later he left.<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention> had told
            me what to expect...so I followed the sailor. He went down to the wharf....I was behind
            him with a revolver in my pocket. As he started to get into a fishing boat....I captured
            him...and also these...</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Chatter of excited voices. Gavel.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>You'll find, <mention ref="prefect"> Monsieur Le Prefect</mention>, that those ate the missing
            jewels.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker>That is a lie! He is lying to save his friend!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>Oh, no, I'm not! The fisherman is waiting outside the room
            now.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>Have him brought in!</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Footsteps. Chatter of voices.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Henri</speaker><stageDirect>About fifty. French accent. Voluble</stageDirect> <stageDirect>Fading
                in</stageDirect> Henri Borel has done nothing! Only what <mention ref="charel">Monsieur Charel</mention> pays him to
            do...and now he is brought into the surette [sic] like a criminal!</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Commotion. Gavel. Voices subside.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>Henri Borel...are those the jewels the ones that were given to
            you by <mention ref="charel">Monsieur Charel</mention> last night?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Henri</speaker>Oui, <mention ref="prefee"> Monsieur le Prefee</mention>! But you must no blame me. I only do
            what I am told to do...to sail with them to Corsica and give them to <mention ref="charel">Monsieur Charel</mention>'s
            brother. Just as I have done a hundred times before.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Charel</speaker><stageDirect>violently</stageDirect> He lies! I have never seen
            him in my life!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Henri</speaker>I lie? Henri Baptiste Borel, born in your own home town of
            Ajaccio...I that have known you since you were a boy? Sacre nom du chien,
            monsieur...what game do you play?!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Monsieur le Prefect...the dagger on the table in front of
            you...may I show it to this man?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Prefect</speaker>Of course.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker><stageDirect>After a moment</stageDirect> Henri Borel...have
            you ever seen this dagger before?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Henri</speaker>Mais oui! Of course I have seen it. My brother made it. He is
            the finest sword maker in Ajaccio...he made it for <mention ref="charel">Monsieur Charel</mention>....</ln>
        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker><stageDirect>Suddenly</stageDirect> Look out! Charel! He's
            drawing his revolver! Stop him!</ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Revolver shot</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><music>Up fast into bridge.</music></ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>Footsteps on cobblestones.</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker><stageDirect>After footsteps are established</stageDirect>
                Well,<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>, Charel solved it for you very simply
            by committing suicide.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Oh, no,<mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention>, it was already
            solved...thanks to your very excellent sleuthing.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker><stageDirect>Bumbling happily</stageDirect> I didn't do
            anything much.<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>. Just what you told me to. By the
            way...I still don't understand Charel's motive for murdering Madame Corvey.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>It was a combination of motives. Jealousy at her announcing her
            engagement to the Duc...and anger at realizing that she had replaced the jewels in Lord
            Shipton's heirloom without telling him. Henri Borel made it very clear tonight that they
            had been [in] partnership as smugglers for years.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>One of our most unusual cases.
                <stageDirect>Facetiously</stageDirect> You know,<mention ref="holmes">
                Holmes</mention>, for a while, I was afraid you were going to end up in the
            guillotine!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker><stageDirect>Chuckling</stageDirect> Did you really, old
            fellow? By the way, there was a certain poetic justice about the case.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>In what way?!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>Did you notice that Charel's dagger has an inscription on the
            blade?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>Yes...but I couldn't translate it.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>It said: "Che la mia ferita sia mortale."</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Watson</speaker>And what does that mean,<mention ref="holmes">
            Holmes</mention>?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>Holmes</speaker>"Let my wound be mortal."</ln>

        <ln><music>Up strong to curtain.</music></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Campbell</speaker>Tonight's <mention ref="holmes">Sherlock Holmes</mention>
            adventure is written by Denis Green and Bruce Taylor and is based on an incident in the
            Sir Arthur Conan Doyle story, "The Adventure of the Illustrious Client." Mr. Rathbone
            appears through the courtesy of Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer and Mr. Bruce through the courtesy
            of Universal Pictures where they are now starring in the <mention ref="holmes">Sherlock
                Holmes</mention> series.</ln>

        <ln><music>Theme up and down under</music></ln>

        <ln><speaker>Campbell</speaker><stageDirect>Out</stageDirect> The Petri Wine Company of San
            Francisco, California, invites you to tune in again next week, same time, same
            station.</ln>
    </script>
</xml>
